Lawrence mss. II, 1920-1924 LMC 1635
Lilly Library
Lawrence mss. II
1920-1924
1986
Lilly Library
David Herbert Lawrence
LMC 1635
1 Box 1 standard
The Lawrence mss. II, 1920-1924, consist of letters and cards from David Herbert Lawrence, 1885-1930, novelist, to Robert Mountsier, 1888-1972, editor.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
David Herbert Lawrence was an English novelist. Robert Mountsier was Lawrence's agent and an editor of The Evening Sun.
Scope and Content Note
The collection covers the period of time, and just afterward, that Mountsier acted as Lawrence's agent in America. Several of the letters describe his relationship with, and opinions of, various American and English publishers, particularly Benjamin W. Huebsch, Martin Secker, and Thomas Seltzer. The letters begin the year before Lawrence left England for Italy, and eventually the United States. He thus writes from England, Italy, Germany, Ceylon, Australia, New Zealand, San Francisco, and Taos, New Mexico. Many of the letters in late 1922 mention Mabel Dodge Luhan and his feelings about living with her generosity but "smothering" attentions. There are also two letter from Frieda (von Richthofen) Lawrence to Mountsier, written on the versos of her husband's letters. Other correspondents present are Robert Mountsier, Giuseppe Prezzolini, Martin Secker, and Thomas Seltzer.
Early in 1923, Lawrence decided to break with Mountsier, apparently after a lengthy visit by Mountsier in Taos. Thus the last twenty letters or so in the collection deal with tying up their business together, including any continuing commissions for Mountsier and Lawrence's 1922 tax reports.
Heretofore unpublished, many of the letters will be in The Letters of D.H. Lawrence, Cambridge edition, volumes 4 and 5 (Lilly PR6023 .A9 Z5 1979).
Related Material
See the Lawrence mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 1986
Lawrence, David Herbert, 1885-1930; Lawrence, Frieda, 1879-1956; Mountsier, Robert, 1888-1972; Huebsch, B. W. (Benjamin W.), 1876-1964; Prezzolini, Giuseppe, 1882-1982; Secker, Martin, 1882-1978; Seltzer, Thomas
- 1920 (Box 1)
- 1921, Jan.-Apr. (Box 1)
- 1921, May-Aug. (Box 1)
- 1921, Sept.-Dec. (Box 1)
- 1922, Jan.-Apr. (Box 1)
- 1922, May-Sept. (Box 1)
- 1922, Oct.-Dec. (Box 1)
- Empty envelopes and mailing labels, 1922 (Box 1)
- 1923 (Box 1)
- 1924 (Box 1)
- n.d. (Box 1)
- Empty envelopes and address labels, n.d. (Box 1)
- Printed (Box 1)